<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Parish churches turn'd into conventicles by serving God therein, and worshiping him otherwise then according to the established liturgy and practice of the Church of England in particular, by reading the communion service or any part thereof in the desk, or plain reasons and undeniable authorities alledged for the reading of the second service, or the communion service when there is no communion at the altar or holy table ... / by Richard Hart, a friend to all the conformable clergy and laity of the true and apostolical Church of England by law established.</title>
            <author>Hart, Richard, Friend to all the conformable clergy and laity of the true and apostolical Church of England.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45736</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H962</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21744</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12684017</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12684017</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65719</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45736)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65719)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 356:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Parish churches turn'd into conventicles by serving God therein, and worshiping him otherwise then according to the established liturgy and practice of the Church of England in particular, by reading the communion service or any part thereof in the desk, or plain reasons and undeniable authorities alledged for the reading of the second service, or the communion service when there is no communion at the altar or holy table ... / by Richard Hart, a friend to all the conformable clergy and laity of the true and apostolical Church of England by law established.</title>
                  <author>Hart, Richard, Friend to all the conformable clergy and laity of the true and apostolical Church of England.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ralph Holt for Obadiah Blagrave ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>British Museum Catalogue indicates Richard Hart is a pseudonym.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Newberry Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Customs and practices.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:65719:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:65719:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>PARISH CHURCHES turn'd into conventicles, BY Serving God therein, and worſhiping him o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then according to the eſtabliſhed Liturgy and Practice of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IN PARTICULAR, By reading the Communion Service, or any part thereof in the Desk.</p>
            <p>OR Plain Reaſons and undeniable Authorities alledged for the reading of the ſecond Service, or the Communion Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, when there is no Communion, at the Altar, or Holy Table, in an Epiſtle dedicated to all the Reverend Clergy of the Church of <hi>England</hi> who read it in the Desk.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Richard Hart,</hi> a Friend to all the conformable Clergy and Laity of the true and Apoſtolical Church of <hi>England</hi> by Law Eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <q xml:lang="grc">
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <bibl>Damaſcen.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Ralph Holt,</hi> for <hi>Obadiah Blagrave,</hi> at the <hi>Bear</hi> in St. <hi>Paul's Church-Yard.</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:65719:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:65719:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend Fathers.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>TO ſeek out an Excuſe of this my Boldneſs, and to arm the Acknowledgment of a Fault with the Reaſons for it, might better ſhew I knew I did amiſs, than any way dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the Attempt: therefore I intend to carry no other Olive-Branch of Interceſſion than a cleer manifeſtation of the Truth of ſuch things wherein I do humbly conceive you Err, ſome of you; not wilfully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, yet for want of a due and ſerious Conſideration of the great Obligation of humane Laws in things which in their own nature are indifferent. One of which is the place for reading of the ſecond Service; which place, without all doubt, is a thing in its own nature indifferent: But when a lawful Authority ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>points a certain place, although in its own nature the place remains ſtill indifferent, yet the uſe of that place is not indifferent, but becomes neceſſary by reaſon of the command, to which the neceſſity of Obedience is inſeparably annexed.</p>
            <p>If this be a falſe Poſition, I have nothing more to ſay, but if it be true, then do you err in point of Practice, which is not according to the eſtabliſh'd Rule, our Church appointing one certain place, and you read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in another; and ſo by this means teaching the People this dangerous Principle, that things indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:65719:3"/>in their own Nature, remain ſo as to their uſe after a lawful Command, for the doing, or not doing of any ſuch indifferent things, as they were before ſuch Command or Prohibition. A Principle which undermines the Foundation of the whole Church; and being once admitted, leaves us naked and defenceleſs againſt all the Weapons that are or may be formed, either by the Papiſt or Puritan, againſt the moſt glorious Church in the World. And if we, who proſeſs our ſelves to be Sons of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſhould embrace this miſchievous Tenet, our Church will be ſo much militant againſgt her ſelf, that her Enemies will in a very ſhort time become Triumphant. They ſeeing your practice evidently built upon this ſandy Fo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndation, do on all ſides hit us in the Teeth with theſe things, and laugh us to ſcorn.</p>
            <p>Why do you charge us with Nonconformity and Diſobedience to humane Laws, which are but things indifferent, notwithſtanding the Command. (ſay they) for do not moſt of your Clergy eſteem them as ſuch, when they omit what Rite and Ceremony they pleaſe, though never ſo ſtrictly injoined by the ſupreme Authority? Do theſe things oblige our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and are theirs only free? If it be ſo, then we perceive plainly that the only way to enjoy liberty of Conſcience, is to be a Clergy-Man of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now what ſhall we ſay to theſe things? If we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the matter of Fact, our Church Enemies charge us with Impudence, if we confeſs it (as to keep our ſelves from lying we are forc'd to do) then they charge our reverend Clergy with the ſame Crimes we uſually appropriate to the greateſt Phanatick, <hi>viz.</hi> Diſobedience to the lawful Magiſtrate, and Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to the eſtabliſh'd Orders of the Church. How
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:65719:3"/>to avoid the Horns of this Dilemma, I do ſincerely declare I know not.</p>
            <p>I ſhould be very glad if any of you would be pleas'd to tell me a full Anſwer that I may give to theſe troubleſom People, who have gagg'd me ſo often with theſe things, that I am altogether become dumb, and am aſhamed to receive ſo many Baffles from thoſe Fools who make a mock of Sin.</p>
            <p>I thank God I can defend my ſelf well enough a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all the frivolous and captious Exceptions which have been either made or taken by the Recuſant or the Diſſenter againſt the eſtabliſhed Doctrine, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline and Worſhip of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> but if they talk to me of any thing that is ſaid or done in our Churches, which is not warranted by the XXXIX. Articles, by the Book of Canons, by the Book of Common Prayer, or by the conſtant univerſal Practice of the Catholick Church of Chriſt; they had as good talk to me of the Roman Breviary, or the Engliſh Directory, and I can as ſoon juſtify the ſaying, either of them in our Churches, as any thing I have before mentioned.</p>
            <p>True it is, that we have a moſt excellent Liturgy eſtabliſhed by the Law of the Land, but in very many places little or no care had that the Subjects may have it whole and intire, without mangling and curtailing in ſuch a ſhameful manner that by theſe ſacrilegious ways our ſacred Book of Common Prayer is become contemptible, and the People are come to this paſs, even downright to declare their abhorrence of our religious Aſſemblies; when inſtead of paying that ſolemn Worſhip to God, which by the Laws of our Nation are devoted to him, we worſhip him after our own Imaginations, and hereby offer him the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of Fools, which he will in no wiſe accept.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:65719:4"/>
            <p> Although I could inſtance in ſundry Particulars, yet at this time I ſhall onely name one, which is reading the Communion Service in the Desk, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by you take upon you to break an authoriſed Order of our Church, and to make a new one: The appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of which Order pertaineth not to private Men (as our Church ſaith very truly) therefore no Man ought to take in hand, or preſume to appoint or alter any publick or common Order in Chriſt's Church, except he be lawfully called and authorized thereunto.</p>
            <p>Either you believe this to be true or falſe; if true, then you wilfully and contemptuouſly tranſgreſs and break a common Order and Diſcipline whenſoever you omit or alter a Rite or Ceremony appointed by the Church, which though in its ſelf conſidered, is but a ſmall thing, yet by reaſon of the Contempt, that is inſeparably annexed to the Offence in a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon knowing, and being verily perſwaded of the Truth hereof, it is no ſmall Offence before God, that is in plain Engliſh, it is a very great Sin.</p>
            <p>Now if it ſhould ſo happen that any of you are of another Perſwaſion, and ſo you are Diſſenters in your Judgment, as well as in your Practice, why then did you ſubſcribe to the ſecond Article mentioned in the XXXVI. Canon, and play faſt and looſe with God Almighty, and put Tricks upon your own Mother the Church of <hi>England?</hi> Do you think that God will be mocked, or permit his holy Spouſe to be cheated? How can you, or any other be ſaid to uſe the Form preſcribed in publick Prayer and Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Sacraments, and none other, which you have promiſed to do by your Subſcription, which is a ſacred Tie, and yet immediately after willingly omit, or alter any one Rite or Ceremony, without a great perfidiouſneſs!</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:65719:4"/>
            <p> As to the Point of reading the Communion Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice when there is no Communion, I do poſitively aſſert, that it is appointed by our Church to be read at the North ſide of the Holy Table, and that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever reads it at any other place, breaks the Order of our Church, and if he doth it through his private Judgment willingly and purpoſely (as he cannot be preſumed to do otherwiſe who is fully convinced that the Church hath ſo appointed it) he doth not only offend againſt the common order of the Church, but hurteth the Authority of the Magiſtrate, and wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Conſciences of the weak Brethren!</p>
            <p>Herein I have two ſorts of Perſons to deal withal, one plainly confeſſing, that 'tis-commanded by the Church, and thereby ſaving me the trouble of a Proof, but ſaying withal that he is at liberty notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Command, and he offers ſome ſeeming Reaſons for his altering the appointed Place, and ſays they are ſufficient to juſtify his Practice both before God and Man, and whether they be ſo or no, you will ſee by and by.</p>
            <p>There is another ſort of men who knowing not how to juſtify their preſent Practice contrary to a plain Injunction of Authority, are forced to make uſe of an <hi>Index Expurgatorius,</hi> and having thereby in their own Conceit quite expung'd the Rubrick as to this Purpoſe, confidently tell me there is no ſuch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand when there is no Communion, therefore no diſobedience to that Authority which they own, and are both ready and willing to obey.</p>
            <p>To every one of you (dear Sirs) who own the thing which others deny, I muſt anſwer with an <hi>ex ore tuo te Judico:</hi> for you ingeniouſly confeſs that 'tis commanded by the Church, and yet at the ſame time moſt diſingeniouſly prefer a corrupt Practice of ſome
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:65719:5"/>ill principled men before your known Duty.</p>
            <p>And for this you make ſeveral Pleas. Firſt, you ſay 'tis the Cuſtom of moſt Pariſh Churches to read the ſecond Service in the Desk: and Cuſtom in the major part of any Society, hath the force of a Law, and a Law which is introduced by Cuſtom, is as much a Law as any Statute Law of the Land, becauſe a Law doth not <hi>recipere magis &amp; minus,</hi> and if you do obey that Law which Cuſtom hath made ſo, you are as much obedient to the Law, as he that obeys an Act of Parliament. But how weak and inſufficient this Plea is, judg you your own ſelves, when you have well conſidered the falſe Notions of ſuch a Cuſtom, which you too faſt do run away with, not making a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſtinction between <hi>corruptela,</hi> and <hi>conſuetudo,</hi> and little regarding the ſmall force ſuch a Cuſtom (ſetting aſide the Corruption) hath to ſway any Mans Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment who is rightly informed of the truth of this matter.</p>
            <p>Now certainly moſt true it is, that a conſtant uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Cuſtom or Practice of a whole National Church hath the force of a Law, and ought without all doubt to be obſerved; but then you muſt take this along with you, provided that no poſitive Law of the Kingdom intervene to annul that Cuſtom, Practice, or what you will call it, otherwiſe the Rule is falſe: For to plead Cuſtom againſt poſitive Law, is to plead that which was the Law againſt that which is the Law; the ſole intent of all poſitive Laws, being to take away the binding power of all cuſtomary Laws to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, otherwiſe there would be two Laws in being at one and the ſame time, commanding the one contrary to the other, which would certainly breed that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion which all poſitive Laws are deſigned to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:65719:5"/>
            <p> I Pray Gentlemen be pleaſed to conſider what Miſchief you do both to Church and State, by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring ſuch a Cuſtom as this before an eſtabliſhed Law to the contrary: Do not you by this means turn our golden Liturgy into a leaden Directory, and the beſt of Churches into the worſt of Conventicles? You may laugh as much you pleaſe, but this is a great Truth, becauſe it is neither the Place, nor the Number of Perſons meeting together that makes a Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, for theſe may be Riots, Routs, or unlawful Aſſemblies: but that which doth conſtitute it a Conventicle, and from which it receives its true De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination, is the meeting in any Place above ſuch a limited Number, and Serving God otherwiſe than according to the eſtabliſhed Liturgy and Practice of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which may be done in a Church as well as a Barn, as ſad Experience tells. It is only the Obſervation, or non-Obſervation of all the Orders, Rites, and Ceremonies (and none other) which are appointed in and by the Common Prayer and Book of Canons, which gives it the Denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Church or Conventicle. If all the Orders be regularly obſerved without Addition or Diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, either in Matter or Form, 'tis a true Church, and a right Church: but if any thing be Said, Sung, or done, in Church, or in private Houſes (where there are above ſuch a Number as the Law ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>points) as the publick Worſhip of God, which is not warranted by the Book of Common Prayer, or by ſome Law of the ſupreme Governour both in Church and State, although hereby it ceaſes not to be a true Church, yet it ceaſes to be a right Church, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mences to be a true Conventicle, for I know no Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium between a right Church, and a true Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, every Meeting upon the pretence of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:65719:6"/>of Religion; being the one or the other.</p>
            <p>And ſo every Perſon in Holy Orders that officiates at Divine Service, is either a thorough Conformiſt, or a Non-conformiſt, I know no medium in an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed Church (as ours is) but if there be, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be informed of theſe things, to wit, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, or how few of the eſtabliſhed Prayers may be ſaid? How many of the Rites and Ceremonies may be uſed? Which may be omitted, which altered? Which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther omitted nor altered? And yet the ſame Perſon doing or omitting any of theſe things, may be, and remain a true Conformiſt, for if they be not li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited to a certain number, then he that uſes only the Lords Prayer, uſes part of the Book of Common Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and the moſt material part too, and may as truly be eſteemed as true a Conformiſt as he that uſes a great deal more, and yet falls ſhort of the whole, either as to Matter of Form; for whoſoever he be that alters or diminiſhes willingly in either, he is ſo far a Nonconformiſt, and how much farther he will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, no body knows but himſelf; but this we know by common Experience, break Ice in one place, it will crack in a great many more. He that wilfully breaks the ſmalleſt order of the Church, is fleſht for greater matters. How true therefore is that ſaying, <hi>MINIMUM NON EST NON NEG<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIGERE MINIMA?</hi> And what a great deal of Miſchief in the Church would this ſmall Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence prevent, if it were believed and put in Practice? for then there would not be ſo many <hi>Secundum uſum's</hi> as there are nowadayes. Heretofore it was only <hi>Secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum uſum Sarum, ſecundum uſum Herefordenſem, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum uſum Bangorenſem, ſecundum uſum Eboracenſem, ſecundum uſum Lincolnienſem;</hi> theſe were all prime Places, Cathedralls all, and yet at the beginning of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:65719:6"/>the Reformation this was thought to be a great Grievance.</p>
            <p>But now every Pariſh, be it never ſo inconſiderable, preſcribes to a <hi>Secundum uſum; ſecundum Uſum</hi> this Pariſh, <hi>ſecundum uſum</hi> that Pariſh; and ſo you may go on, and name all the Pariſhes of <hi>England</hi> as far as the Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> upon <hi>Tweed,</hi> and ſo many ſeveral Churches, ſo many <hi>ſecundum uſum's</hi> there are, and yet the Rule by which they be all to walk, is all one and the ſame. Now from henceforth (ſay's the Church of <hi>England</hi> in her Preface concerning the Service of the Church) all the whole Realm ſhall have but one Uſe, and for this very purpoſe was a Liturgy compoſed to remedy the great Diverſities in ſaying and ſinging in Churches, a Remedy very ſage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contrived, but to no purpoſe, becauſe never put in Practice. So much for that.</p>
            <p>The next Plea I have heard ſome of you make uſe of, is, that the Biſhop of your Dioceſs doth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe with your Obedience as to ſeveral Rubricks, and in particular to this, which is a plain Confeſſion that 'tis enjoin'd by the ſupreme Authority, otherwiſe, what need is there of a Diſpenſation? which being ſo, what Authority hath the Biſhop, or all the Biſhops together (I ſay this with humble Submiſſion to that Holy Order, for which no Man hath a greater Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration than my ſelf) what Authority, I ſay, have they to diſpenſe with a Duty injoyned by Act of Parliament? ſure I am, that they may as well Diſpenſe with the woollen Act, or the Act prohibiting Iriſh Cattel, as with the Act of Uniformity. Doth not the Book of Common Prayer itſelf, which is eſtabliſhed by the ſaid Act, reſtrain all Dioceſans from making any order concerning any Doubt ariſing about the Uſe and Practice of any thing in the Book, any order that is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:65719:7"/>contrary to any thing contained in this Book?</p>
            <p>Now from hence I argue, If the Communion Service be not appointed by the Rubrick to be read at the North ſide of the Table when there is no Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and ſo the reading it in the Desk be not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to any thing contained in the book, why do you require a needleſs Diſpenſation, and if it be contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry how can be Biſhop grant it?</p>
            <p>When publick Orders and Conſtitutions have been received, and have taken place, ſhall general Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence thereunto ceaſe to be exacted, in caſe this or that private Perſon led with ſome probable Conceit, ſhould make open Declaration that <hi>A. B.</hi> Biſhop of, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> doth diſpenſe with me concerning ſuch a Rubrick? And although 'tis granted that the Biſhop himſelf is a Perſon in a publick Charge and Authority, and all Curates are bound to obey him in <hi>omnibus licitis &amp; honeſtis;</hi> yet if the Dioceſan ſhould command all under his Juriſdiction to read the Communion Service in the Desk, the Biſhops Mandate without all doubt muſt give place to the King's Laws, and in all ſuch Caſes the King muſt be obeyed, and not the Biſhop, becauſe it is neither <hi>licitum</hi> nor <hi>honeſtum,</hi> to obey a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſubordinate Power, when the Supreme commands otherwiſe: Beſides, when publick conſent of the whole hath eſtabliſhed any thing, every Man's Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being thereunto compared, is private, howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his Calling be to ſome kind of publick Charge, otherwiſe there could be no means poſſible to attain to any Peace or Quietneſs either in Church or State, unleſs the probable Voice of every intire Society or Body Politick, over-rule all private of like Nature in the ſame.</p>
            <p>And this is our Caſe exactly; for 'tis determined by the King with the Conſent of the three Eſtates,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:65719:7"/>repreſenting the whole Body of the Kingdom, where the ſecond Service ſhall be ſaid; and this is not alterable according to our Laws, but by the ſame full Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity by which it was enacted; not by any ſingle Perſon, if he be a Subject, nor by any one of three Eſtates, nor by all together without the King, which is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to over-rule the frivolous Plea of a Diſpenſation, which can never be defended without overturning the Government, by altering the Frame and Conſtitution thereof: to ſuch ſad Exigents are they reduced who undertake to defend what they have not beforehand well conſidered of: For who would have imagined, that ſo ſmall an Omiſſion as this at firſt ſight ſeems to be, ſhould ſwell to ſuch a mountainous Crime as to equal the Popes Pride in contending with the King for the Supremacy, and by little and little to ſubvert his Government: which puts me in mind of a Paſſage I have met with in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> which jumps even with the matter in hand.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paulus Aemylius,</hi> a noble Roman, and one of the Conſuls, afterwards choſen to be one of the number of Prieſts, whom the Romans called <hi>Augurs;</hi> when he did any thing belonging to his Office of Prieſthood, he did it with great Experience, Judgment, and Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence; leaving all other Thoughts, and without omitting any ancient Ceremony, or adding to any new; contending oftentimes with his Companions in things which ſeemed light and of ſmall moment, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring unto them that though we do preſume the Gods are eaſy to be pacified, and that they readily pardon all Scapes and Faults committed by Negligence, yet if it were no more but for reſpect of Common-Wealths ſake, they ſhould not ſlightly, nor careleſly diſſemble, nor paſs over Faults committed in thoſe matters: For no Man (ſaith he) at the firſt, that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:65719:8"/>any Fault, doth alone trouble the State of the Commonwealth, but withall we muſt think he leaveth the Grounds of civil Government that is not careful to keep the Inſtitutions of ſmall matters as well as great. The Inference is obvious, and I muſt leave it to you to make the Application. And now I have done with the Plea of a Diſpenſation.</p>
            <p>The next is, that it is very inconvenient for the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who by reaſon of the diſtance of the Place cannot hear, and ſo are never the better, they neither know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to what they ſhould pronounce their <hi>Amen,</hi> nor when to ſay it; to which I anſwer experimentally, that though ſometimes it may poſſibly ſo fall out, by reaſon of the low Voice of the Prieſt; yet the ſame Miſchief attends the Desk as well as the Table: For if the Miniſter doth not audibly and diſtinctly read the Prayers (as in too many places he doth not) the People are as little edified by their being read in the Desk as at the Altar; and if they be audibly and diſtinctly read, they may be heard as well at the Table, as in the Desk: So that the Fault (if any be) is not occaſioned by the diſtance of the Place, ſo much as through the indiſcretion of the Reader, which he may help himſelf.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe this Inconvenience were general, and as great as you ſeem to make it, yet we cannot ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that the Governours of our Church ſhould be ſo ſhort-Sighted as not to diſcern it, nor yet ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudent as not to provide a Remedy for it: But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, be it never ſo inconvenient, this may be deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in a regular way, by thoſe who are authoriſed thereunto, and the Inconvenience taken away by thoſe who are veſted with a legal Power for that Purpoſe (if they think fitting ſo to have it.) But for any private Pariſh Curate to take upon him, not only
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:65719:8"/>to Diſpute, but to Judg of the Conveniency and Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency of a Law firmly eſtabliſhed by the Conſent of the whole Nation, and thereupon to alter the Law after his own Model, is no leſs a piece of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolence then to take upon him to be King, Biſhop, and Prieſt of his own Pariſh, by impoſing his own Laws upon the People, and cancelling thoſe of his Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors.</p>
            <p>Some of you ſay that it is very indecent for the Prieſt to go out of the Desk up to the Altar in his Surplice, and to come back again with his Surplice ſtill on, to the Homily or Sermon (which by the way, being part of Adminiſtration of the divine Service, is to be performed with the Surplice on) and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn back again to read the Prayer for the Church Militant, as they are appointed to do. In Anſwer whereunto, although my former Anſwer to the Plea of Inconvenience might ſerve very well, yet by the way I cannot but obſerve that theſe very Men, who have been ſo Eagle-ſighted as to ſpy out this great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decency; yet when the ſame thing is done at another place, they cannot diſcern the Indecency: For when a Child is to be Baptized at the Font, they can go out of the Desk in their Surplice after the ſecond Leſſon, and return to the ſame place without any Bluſhing, as if the going up to the Eaſt end of the Church in a Surplice, were a very unſeemly Poſture, and yet going down to the Weſt end in the ſame Garment, were a very comely Geſture. <hi>Riſum teneatis?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Have you any more to ſay in your own defence? I pray let me hear it, that I may leave no Objection unanſwered: For if I cannot Anſwer all that can be ſuppoſed againſt my Aſſertion, I had better ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; and if there be the leaſt colour of Reaſon or Argument on your Behalfs, I am willing to admit it,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:65719:9"/>and ſtop my Pen, as ſoon as you have ſtop'd my Mouth with a convincing Reaſon.</p>
            <p>You ſay that our Governours connive at the Omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of your Duty, they wink at your Practice, and take no notice of your doings, the Laws are not exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted upon you, as they are upon other Perſons, you hear of no Inditements at the Aſſizes or Seſſions, no Information in the Crown Office, and this to you is eſteem'd a ſufficient Warrant for your preſent Practice, this ſeems to you a tacit Declaration, that the ſupreme Power doth not deſire his Law ſhould be obey'd in this particular.</p>
            <p>And by reaſon of this Impunity you fancy that 'tis his Majeſties Pleaſure that you ſhould take this Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty againſt his Laws; and therefore, than I am juſtly to be Blam'd, who being but a private Perſon have expreſſed greater Severity againſt you than the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate himſelf; because I have charged you with the Guilt of Sin, when the Magiſtrate doth not ſo much as puniſh you. Whereas in truth 'tis not I that lay any ſuch thing to your Charge, but the Church of <hi>England,</hi> whoſe Words I have only quoted, that the wilful and contemptuous Tranſgreſſion, and breaking of a common Order and Diſcipline (as this is, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we now Treat) is no ſmall Offence before God, as I told you before.</p>
            <p>Is not this the full Subſtance of your Plea? and is not this your Logick? You are not puniſhed for your Diſobedience: <hi>Ergo,</hi> 'tis lawful to Diſobey. You fancy 'tis his Majeſties Pleaſure that you ſhould not Obey: <hi>Ergo,</hi> it is ſo. His Majeſties Law is not Executed: <hi>Ergo,</hi> 'tis no binding Law. What a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Nonſequiturs</hi> are here? What kind of Syllogiſm will you make of this? There is ſuch a Steeple as <hi>Tenterden</hi> Steeple: <hi>Ergo,</hi> 'tis the cauſe of <hi>Goodwin</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:65719:9"/>Sands, as good an <hi>Ergo</hi> as any of the former.</p>
            <p>But I muſt not let this paſs thus. You ſay 'tis his Majeſties Pleaſure you ſhould enjoy your Liberty in this Matter; it may be ſo for ought I know, but if it ſhould prove otherwiſe, as it is more than an even lay that it doth, then have you been overbold with his Sacred Majeſty, by pretending to be of his Cabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net Councel, which is more than probable that you are not.</p>
            <p>We his poor Subjects are ſatisfied with his known Will and Pleaſure, publickly declared in his Laws, without liſtening at the Privy Council Door to know what his ſecret Will is, before it is his Pleaſure to make it known: And as ſoon as his Majeſty graciouſly vouchſafes to declare any thing in Oppoſition to that which is eſtabliſhed by Law, I ſhall obey it with all Submiſſion and Reverence, humbly and ſilently ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſcing in the Determination of his Will and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, which to me is, and ſhall ever be a Law as binding as any Act of Parliament ſince the Conqueſt. In the mean time, if his Majeſty hath whiſpered this ſo ſoftly, that none could hear it but your ſelves, blame not me who know nothing of the matter, and yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding have great cauſe to think that my Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg is not inferior to yours in this Particular.</p>
            <p>If his Majeſty hath communicated his private Will to you, ſpeak it out, and let us know it; and you ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence me for ever: But I pray have a care how you make it an Argument to juſtify what you do, by ſaying that the King takes no notice of that Licence you have given your ſelf; and do not perſwade your ſelves, that 'tis as good as if you had a Licence from his Majeſty himſelf for your unlawful Practice, for ſo I muſt make bold to call it until I know further of this matter.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:65719:10"/>
            <p> I ſee no Proof ſo much as offered at for his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Pleaſure in this Affair, except it be the Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>execution of his Laws, which may be imputed to the Neglect of his Officers and Miniſters in the Diſcharge of their Duty. But if to ſerve your turn you will ſay 'tis an Argument of his Will and not of their Neglect; you muſt unavoidably ſerve ſomebodies Turn beſides your own, therefore you had better let this Argument alone, leſt ſome others take it out of your Mouths, and make uſe of it againſt your ſelves.</p>
            <p>Another pretty ſort of Argument others make uſe of, which though it little deſerves an Anſwer, yet I ſhall briefly ſay ſomething to it, and ſo finiſh with you worthy Gentlemen who confeſs the Command, and yet practiſe quite Oppoſite to it. You ſay that the People are not pleaſed with it, otherwiſe you would very willingly go up to the Altar, or Holy Table, but if you ſhould, the People would go out of the Church, and perhaps come no more. In good time! Muſt the Orders of the Church hang upon ſo ſlender a Thred, as the liking, or diſliking of an ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant Multitude? Muſt the Shepherd go whither the Sheep would have him, and no further, for fear of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing the Sheep? Is the Government of our Church ſo precarious? If this be the Caſe, you may ſhut up the Church Doors and write over them <hi>DOLENS DICO, GEMENS DENUNTIO, SA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CERDOTIUM QOUD APUD NOS INTUS CECIDIT FORISDIU STA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RE NON POTER IT: CITO ENIM ACTUM ERIT DE ECCLESIA AN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GLICANA.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I have ſomething to ſay to you Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Sirs, who ſay that there is no Rubrick, neither was it ever the Intention of the Church, that there
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:65719:10"/>ſhould be one for the reading the Communion Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice at the North ſide of the Table when there is no Communion; You cannot ſee ſuch a Rubrick. What? are there no Rubricks at all to direct the orderly read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thoſe Prayers and other Religious Duties which are to be performed when there is no Communion? Do you never Preach but when there is a Communion? Yes, yes, there is a plain Rubrick for it, Then ſhall follow the Sermon. You can read that Sirs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a pair of Spectacles I perceive very well; but kind Sirs, according to your own Conſtruction of the Rubricks, this is only when there is a Communion: for the next immediate Rubrick is, Then ſhall the Prieſt return to the Lord's Table. Can any one be properly ſaid to return to the Place he was not at be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? And if he was at it before, then there muſt be a Communion, ſay you; but if there be no Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and the appointed Rubricks ſerve only for Communion-time, then there is no Sermon appointed, ſay I, ſo that either you muſt acknowledg that all the ſame Rubricks belong to the Communion Service when there is no Communion, as well as when there is one, or elſe what will become of your great <hi>Diana</hi> the <hi>SERMON:</hi> Methinks for the dear ſake of that <hi>Unum Neceſſarium,</hi> that <hi>Magnum Oportet;</hi> you ſhould be more kind to that part of the Liturgy, which gives the ſole Authority to your Sermon. I beſeech you (gentle Sirs) deal not ſo unworthily with your own Mother, as to wink hard againſt the Light, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully not to ſee your way, when She commands you to go up to the Altar, and yet to be as quick-ſighted as an Eagle when you aſcend the Pulpit.</p>
            <p>How comes it to paſs that you ſhould be blinder than the Presbyterians, for if you do not ſee this Rubrick of Reading at the North ſide of the Table when there
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:65719:11"/>is no Communion 'tis really ſo, for they ſpied out this hidden Rubrick, and ſain would have been rid of it, it being a great Eye-ſore to them, and they would fain have exchanged Conditions with you, that they might have been ſo blind as not to have ſeen it; but ſince they did too plainly Diſcern it, no remedy now but to deſire the Biſhops at the grand Debate at the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy,</hi> when our gracious King was firſt reſtored to his Crown, that the Miniſter be not required to rehearſe any part of the Liturgy at the Communion Table, ſave only thoſe parts which properly belong to the Lord's Supper, and that at ſuch time onely when the Holy Supper is Adminiſtred. Theſe are the very Words of their Requeſt, by which it appears ſo plain that a blind Man may ſee it, that by the Rubrick be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Communion Office, The Prieſt ſtanding at the North-ſide of the Table ſhall ſay, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians themſelves, who are apt enough to pick holes in the Churches Orders if they be againſt their Humour, yet could not do it here; for they could make no other Conſtruction of it, agreeable either with Senſe or Reaſon, but this; that at all times when any part of the Communion Service was to be read, there lay an Obligation upon all Prieſts, by Virtue only of that Rubrick. And the Prieſt ſtanding, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to read that Part at the Communion Table, when there was no Communion, or elſe to what purpoſe was this Requeſt of theirs? and why did the Reverend Biſhops make ſuch an Anſwer as they did?</p>
            <p>The Anſwer is this, That the Miniſter ſhould not Read the Communion Service at the Communion Table, is not reaſonable to demand, ſince all the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church uſed it, and if we do not obſerve that golden Rule of the venerable Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> let ancient Coſtoms prevail till Reaſon plainly requires the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:65719:11"/>contrary, we ſhall give Offence to ſober Chriſtians by cauſeleſs departure from Catholique Uſage, and a greater Advantage to the Enemies of our Church, than our Berethren I hope would willingly grant. The Prieſt ſtanding at the Communion Table, ſeemeth to give us an Invitation to the Holy Sacrament, and minds us of our Duty, <hi>viz.</hi> To Receive the Holy Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, ſome at leaſt every Sunday; and though we neglect our Duty, 'tis fit the Church ſhould keep her ſtanding.</p>
            <p>Obſerve that, and if you find no reaſon in what the Reverend Biſhops ſay, uſe your Liberty ſtill for a Cloak of Nonconformity, and remember 'tis but a Cloak, and ſuch a one, as you had better be ſtark nak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed than be covered with.</p>
            <p>And now it remains that I ſhould produce ſome unqueſtionable Authorities to back my Reaſons, that it may appear to all unbiaſſed Perſons, That the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all the great Worthies of our Church, who have either occaſionally, or on ſet Purpoſe treated of this matter, is unanimouſly this.</p>
            <p>The Communion Service ought to be read accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Rule Preſcribed in our Book of Common Prayer, at the North ſide of the Table, as well when there is no Communion, as well as when there is one.</p>
            <p>I will begin with the moſt judicious Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> who in his fifth Book, Sect. 30. hath theſe Words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Some</hi> (meaning ſome parts of our Liturgy) <hi>are ſuch, as albeit they ſerve to ſingular good Purpoſe, even when there is no Communion Adminiſtred, nevertheleſs being deviſed at the firſt for that Purpoſe, are at the Table of the Lord for that Cauſe alſo commonly Read.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next Authority is the great Arch Biſhop <hi>Land,</hi> ſecond unto the Reverend Father <hi>Hooker,</hi> only in time, who in a Speech in the <hi>Star Chamber,</hi> to which
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:65719:12"/>very few of you can pretend to be Strangers, ſay's thus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Eleventh Innovation is the Reading of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Service at the Communion Table or the Altar.</hi> To this I can truly ſay that ſince my own Memory this was in uſe in very many Places, as being moſt proper: (for thoſe Prayers are then Read which both precede, and follow the Communion) and by little and little this ancient Cuſtom was altered, and in thoſe places firſt where the Emiſſaries of this Faction came to Preach. And now if any one in Authority offer to reduce this ancient Courſe of the Church, 'tis by and by called an Innovation. Secondly, with this the Rubricks of the Common Prayer-Book agree; for the firſt Rubrick after the Communion tells us that upon Holydaies, though there be no Communion, yet all elſe that's appointed at the Communion ſhall be read. Shall be read? that's true, but where? Why the laſt Rubrick before the Communion tells us, that the Prieſt ſtanding at the North ſide of the Holy Table, ſhall ſay the Lord's Prayer with that which follows. So that not only the Communion, but the Prayers which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company the Communion (which are commonly called the Second Service) are to be read at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion Table: Therefore if this be an Innovation, 'tis made by the Rubricks, not by the Prelates.</p>
            <p>Now let us ſee what the Right Reverend Biſhop of <hi>Norwich,</hi> Dr. <hi>Sparrow,</hi> ſay's to this Matter. In his <hi>Rational</hi> of the Common Prayer <hi>p.</hi> 239. thus he ſay's.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Private and ſolitary Communions of the Prieſt the Church allows not, and therefore when other cannot be had, ſhe appoints only ſo much of the Service as relates not of neceſſity to a private Communion, and that to be ſaid at the Holy Table, and upon good Reaſon. The Church thereby keeping as it were her Ground, viſibly
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:65719:12"/>minding us of what She deſires and labors towards our more frequent Acceſs to that Holy Table.</hi> Mark the ſeveral Reaſons, and weigh the great Authority of this famous Triumvirate of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and then Read the Second Service hereafter in the Desk if you can.</p>
            <p>There be ſome others of no mean Credit in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who have poſitively aſſerted the ſame thing, <hi>viz.</hi> Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> in his Introduction to Arch Biſhop <hi>Laud</hi>'s Life <hi>p.</hi> 22. Mr. <hi>Elborow</hi> in his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the Book of Common Prayer <hi>p.</hi> 98. <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond le Strang</hi> in his Alliance of Divine Offices <hi>p.</hi> 122, 123. to which I may add a fourth, which is Dr. <hi>Combers</hi> in his Companion to the Altar, the Page I have forgot, though the Matter I very well remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</p>
            <p>Now if after all theſe Reaſons and Authorites there remains any Doubt, as I believe there may do with thoſe that are reſolved to doubt, that they may have ſome Colour for their reſtleſs Oppoſition to the Churches wholeſom Inſtitutions; I have one thing more to ſay, which becauſe it hath wrought upon ſome, and not only Convinced them, but Converted, as obſtinate as they ſeemed to be, I am in good Hopes it may have the ſame Operation upon ſome others. Let me intreat all you that have any Kindneſs left for the diſtreſſed Church of <hi>England,</hi> to caſt an impartial Eye upon the Forms of Common Prayer, upon ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Occaſions of Faſting and Thanksgiving, ſet forth by Authority, ſhall I ſay, ſince the King's happy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoration, or ſince the bleſſed Reformation? Peruſe them all if you pleaſe, and you ſhall find that in none of them all is there a Communion appointed, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny appears to be intended: but only ſo much of the Communion Service is therein preſcribed to be Read
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:65719:13"/>as on other Holydays is by the Common Prayer Book appointed to be Read when there is no Communion, and yet 'tis ſaid expreſly, The Prieſt ſtanding at the North ſide of the Table ſhall ſay, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What more clear than this, to tell us the meaning of the Rubrick in the Book of Common Prayer, unleſs it be the Practice of the Prime Churches in <hi>England,</hi> the King's Chappel, the Cathedrals, the two Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, and many Orthodox Pariſh Churches, to wit, that of Dr. <hi>Hicks,</hi> that of Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> that of Dr. <hi>Dove,</hi> and if I be not Miſinformed that of Mr. <hi>Pelling,</hi> all Famous, Reverend, and Worthy Divines within the City of <hi>London,</hi> and I queſtion not but the pious Example of ſuch conſcientious Men, hath had an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence upon ſome parts of the Country, ſome I am ſure I know, and others I have heard of; I pray God increaſe their Number, not by confounding the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of any who do otherwiſe, but by converting their Judgments, and confounding thoſe Devices they make uſe of to hinder all manner of Impreſſion that can be made upon them either by Reaſon or Authority; the chiefeſt of which I find to be a <hi>Ne videamur ſemel er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>râſſe.</hi> A Principle too bad to be own'd, and yet too true to be denyed: Recommending you to God's Grace, I take my Leave of you all, leaving this ſhort ſaying with you, <hi>Veritas eſt magna &amp; praevalebit.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Chriſtianus mihi Nomen eſt, Catholicus Cognomen. R. H.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:65719:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
